Our next talk about FFI and Miri at
8,000 safe bolts per second is coming
from Nira, who is on the libs team, is
compiler engineer in Hex Cat, and also
like me suffers a significant caffeine
addiction. So, please welcome Nira.
>> Hi.
Um,
thanks for [snorts] coming here. God,
that's a lot of you. Oh god, you're
going to give me stage fright.
Um, so this talk, very Oh, the thing is
not on. Why is it not on? There it is.
It's on now.
This talk about FFI and Miri
uh,
definitely very different from the
previous one. I believe Antonio was
could be quoted as saying that that talk
was about people. This talk is about one
person. This talk is about one person's
descent into madness trying to implement
whatever that nonsense is up there in
Miri.
>> [snorts]
>> And made it into a debugger by accident
kind of.
I'm Nira.
Um, that's my GitHub. That's my Blue Sky
if you want to see what I've been doing.
Warning from my Blue Sky.
Somewhere about me. I'm a compiler
engineer right now. I work at Hex Cat
uh, also at Rust and L uh, on the Rust
compiler full time. I'm working on a
bunch of stuff. Move traits if some of
you might not know about that. And I'm
also on the libs team.
I used to work on embedded Linux. That's
kind of the reason why I am doing any of
this because I got sidetracked doing
side project after side project after
side project until eventually I needed
more stuff in Miri to work completely
forgetting about the original stuff.
This is entirely tangential to anything
that I was doing a few years ago.
My background before that is completely
unrelated to that as a whole, more so on
the social soft sciences side of things.
And for that particular reason
maybe it's time to to a bit of drama
here, right? You're not all nerds here
to look at a tech presentation about
code. You You need to see some action.
You need to see someone cry.
Um so, Miri is great. Miri can do a lot
of things, right? But,
you know, that's your problem you're on
the Rust project track. But, it is very
limited and slow. Like
it's usable for testing code. That's
what it's meant for. Uh you're not going
to be playing any video games on it. Um
and as you will see, I made it much
worse. This whole 8,000 segfaults per
second thing is
>> [snorts]
>> really bad.
I They'll be fixed eventually.
So, here's the problem when we try to
implement that in Miri, which that it
can just do anything. We have no clue
what it's doing. We don't know what the
FFI code is doing. Miri needs to track a
bunch of stuff about memory state. We
need to track like the providence of
pointers. We need to track whether bytes
are initialized or not. How do you track
that when you are jumping into some
random nonsense code in a probably
different language? Maybe it's C, maybe
it's C++, maybe it's Java.
How are you supposed to figure out what
the code is doing to your memory?
Well, you kind of just will it into
existence.
Um we can't track absolutely everything.
That especially not with a precompiled
binary, which is what I'm targeting that
you can just link against an arbitrary
SO file and call a function and it just
works. Trademark.
We can guess what it did though. We can
limit ourselves to a worst case, which
is significantly better than um
simply just assuming it could have done
anything possible to our memory, which
was the implementation that was used
before for arbitrary FFI.
That does mean we need to track every
memory access.
That's a problem. That's not exactly an
easy straightforward thing to do. Every
single memory access, how big it was,
how how long it was, how wide and thin
and narrow and whether it was a read or
a write.
So,
faced with this problem,
you know, I I grew up in Eastern Europe,
perhaps a more conservative area than a
lot of you. So, my first fallback was to
consult holy scripture of Google search
results
and Stack Overflow.
And I found this.
This random post from 10 darn years ago.
Using sig seg.
It can't be that hard, right? I read
through that. I read some more material
on the topic. Apparently, I wasn't the
first person to come up with the idea
though. Perhaps um few of them have
tried to do it quite the same way as me.
Right? So, we need to uh seg fault. So,
we need to do this with Ptrace.
So, we start up Mary. We fork it into
two processes.
One of them is just going to be handling
those seg faults, doing something. I'll
show you what. The other one is just
going to be Mary. It's going to be
jumping into FFI. It's going to be doing
whatever crazy nonsense.
And when it jumps into the FFI,
we use uh
uh like this is Linux specific because
well, uh with the current
implementation, but we can uh set the
protections on the memory such that it's
prot none. Any access will raise a seg
fault. Well, a seg fault is just a Unix
signal. It's not like anything magic.
You can seg fault and continue running.
That's fine. You're allowed to do that.
The signals don't mean anything if you
don't believe in that garbage. Um
So, every time there's a seg fault,
the supervisor finds out about it
and logs it down somehow and tells it
back to Mary.
We can figure out exactly where the
address happened because the uh seg
fault like
uh information that we get from Ptrace
lets us get like info about what raised
the signal. For seg fault in particular,
that includes the address that caused
the seg fault. Great. Amazing. Lovely.
Perfect. This all works.
Um
but there's still more we need. We need
more information for one. Cuz we know
the address, okay? We know where the
segfault happened. It happened here.
Uh we don't know how big it was. We
don't know if it was a read, if it was a
write, uh if it was a banana. Uh we need
to know a bunch of things about it. And
also we need to make memory keep going
cuz like the code is segfaulted. It's
trying to access memory that is
protected as prot none. So, how is it
supposed to continue? Okay, we know this
happened, and then what? We stop here?
Um
so, we need to mess with the other
process. We need to mess with it as it's
running.
Because, I mean, code is data.
You can just read data, right? This is
what we That's what we do here. We're
the Rust project track. We love parsing
and validating and whatever.
Uh something about validating parsing
and parsing validation. Um so, we can
just read
the data at the instruction pointer
in the other process and you slap it
into this assembler. In this case I was
This was using capstone. This is the
current implementation. That's probably
going to get ripped out
uh for reasons I'll get to in a second.
And we just figure out, okay, we an
access happened at some address.
How big was the access according to the
disassembler? And was it a read or a
write or both? Possibly.
Um this is not perfect for various
reasons of like sometimes a write is
conditional on the read, but it still
gives us a pretty narrow down like worst
case of what memory could have been
accessed by a certain access.
And then from that, what we can get is
uh the information we care about, right?
If a write happened, then that might
have initialized bytes. We don't know
for sure, but we like it could have. And
we know any memory that wasn't written
to definitely didn't get initialized,
which is much better than just just
assuming all memory is initialized, I
guess.
Um
also lets us uh figure out whether
provenance was exposed if the read was
from a pointer.
Um
this does mean a lot of this
architecture specific. This only works
on x86 because a lot of other
architectures have scalable vector
instruction nonsense.
That means that the actual size depends
on what's in some register somewhere and
oh god, that was such a pain to try to
implement. I didn't. I gave up on it.
But it's going to get addressed.
So now, we have a segfault. Uh we need
to recover from it. We know exactly what
happened. We know how big the access
was.
So, we have Petri already set up. We can
mess with registers. You can mess with
memory, right? Code is data.
Uh so, I mean function calls, you can
just do that. Oh wow, there's a lot more
pixels on the screen than I realized.
Um you can just do that. You can just
set the instruction pointer somewhere,
set the stack pointer somewhere into
some just zeroed out area so that you
don't destroy everything.
Um and then just
move yourself [snorts] like into We're
ready to have to write some statics and
then just move yourself into a different
function just out of nowhere.
Um and then we have this like fake
extern C whatever which just like
doesn't actually have a normal calling
convention. It doesn't emp protect on
the current page and then instead of
returning it raises a sig stop which the
parent then has to catch.
This is not a calling convention. I
don't know what this is. This is a crime
against computers.
Okay.
Great.
Let's try it. It surely this like this
is pretty straightforward. The concept
clearly work, right? And the test pass.
Obviously, this is like
they passed with the flags enabled.
There's no trick here. I didn't like
uh set the wrong flags or the the test
aren't testing the right thing. It
worked.
Why did it do this?
It did this so many damn times. I could
not get it to work in CI. It always
worked locally and it always hung in CI
in particular because of course it hung.
It couldn't give me nice error logs.
That would be way too easy, right? And I
can't even see the logs while it's doing
it. So, I just had to wait like however
many hours for it to finish so I could
then read the logs after, which would be
completely useless because the testing
machinery we use doesn't usually print
logs unless there is a hard error.
So, something's hanging. There's a race
condition somewhere.
>> [sighs]
>> Because Unix signals and IPC channel
messages, which we've been using to
actually communicate between these, are
not synced up.
I didn't know this. I could have
probably guessed this if I had looked at
that, right? We have this whole thing at
start at the start up of the um the
splitting into two processes, for
instance. Um when we started the FFI, we
send this thing with some information
written necessary to actually begin the
FFI call, and then we now have that
stupid little confirmation, which wasn't
there before because we need to enforce
an ordering. So, I had to just make that
stupid little confirmation there because
otherwise
on CI and only CI, the racing stop would
be received by the other process before
that damn message, and it would be stuck
forever waiting on a channel that would
never get anything.
Do you understand why I said this is
like a psychological drama?
I hate it. But I fixed it.
I fixed a race condition by
parallelizing it more.
I made this work with many seeds Miri,
where Miri runs multiple processes at
once with different seeds for RNG,
and then debugging that locally got the
hang to reproduce.
And I figured out exactly how to make
this like a lot better. Also compatible
now again with many seeds Miri. We just
have a mutex on the FFI. So Miri can run
however many seeds in parallel at once.
Only one process can be in FFI at once,
which is
actually fixed a pre-existing possible
bug in Miri if you had the old FFI
implementation and many seeds running at
the same time where like a static or a
global in general in some foreign FFI'd
context could be accessed from two
threads at once,
which would normally be impossible. So
now we have a mutex. We have a nice
little mutex. Only one thread can be in
FFI at once.
And if you're running with many seeds,
this will make it actually
behave more normally. If you're messing
with global state, then you're probably
lost anyways, but at least there won't
be data races.
So that is the assembler I was using,
Capstone. It's a great disassembler, to
be clear. Like it's genuinely a really
good disassembler and quite lightweight
for what it is, but I don't need a
disassembler here. I need a magic
machine that tells me operand address
size.
It also made check builds slow. This has
been fixed.
Ralph was bothering the people who
maintain it to add some feature flags so
that we could make
check builds behave differently. It's I
believe just an existing limitation with
cargo the way it's currently set up that
if you're doing FFI, the build
big like foreign code cannot be told,
"Hey, this is a check you don't actually
need to compile." It would still do all
that.
Also the information we need again is
really only accessible on x86 easily.
Otherwise, you start have to you have to
start like handwriting
registers that you have to look at and
figure out exactly how big or wide the
access was by computing that. It's a
headache. I tried it. I genuinely tried
it. It's such a headache. At one point,
I just resorted to assuming all accesses
are like 128 bits cuz no access is
probably going to be much bigger than
that. And then I found out about arm
vector extensions.
So, this is the current situation here.
It just doesn't work on arm.
But,
we don't have to use capstone.
We can bribe someone.
Ixy of Oxide had worked on a project
called the X speaks. Also this assembler
used for some other stuff. Um
but they [clears throat] ran into
something about my work and were like,
"Oh, that's cool. I wonder if the X
speaks could do it better."
And I annoyed the hell out of them
into adding to some of the features that
I need. And oh
god,
they drag got dragged along with me in
this little mental breakdown.
But eventually it worked.
Well,
also I believe Ixy might be watching
this live. So, hello. Um
most of this actually got fixed as as I
understand like
this to do was from a few days ago.
Um a couple
a day before this or something I believe
I was told that this all got merged and
documented. So, congratulations to them.
And hopefully I can actually may put
this into Miri so we can have
one day better cross architecture
support and also less flaky x86.
But that's only part of it because again
this is about bait and switch. Uh we
have uh this bit the whole like reading
like what the other process is doing.
Great. So, okay. So, we can pass
pointers to our memory into code.
Amazing. That's lovely.
But like
usually you also need to get like the
pointers back. Sometimes you need to get
sometimes you will be allocating a
structure somewhere. Like you I don't
know. You're using an allocator library
for instance. And you want to get a
memory allocation. And how do you tell
Miri that that memory allocation is like
real and not just an integer you're
pretending is a pointer?
Cuz it will be UB to for Miri to just
let you
de-reference any arbitrary address and
just pass that straight through to the
hardware. That's a really bad idea.
Right?
So, let's trace allocations.
There is more to it than just this, but
the bulk of it, the interesting bit, um
is the one described here.
Um like okay, this is the example from a
prototypical example function we need to
support. Right?
This
uh is just a wrapper around malloc that
we can't immediately tell, like if this
was a precompiled binary, that it is
malloc. Cuz malloc itself merely will
just shim whatever, not a problem.
Uh this is a problem though, because
this is like
random function returning memory. We
don't know if it's valid.
We shim all the libffi function uh libC
functions that can access memory.
These are the ones in the standard. I
considered shimming all of libC, but was
told this is overkill and definitely
unnecessary. Whatever. Okay, whatever
you say. We do this instead. We have a
bunch of shim functions,
and we just like trap every time yeah
you jump into the normal ones, and then
we move the instruction pointer into the
fake ones. They're both like extern C,
right? They're same calling convention.
It works genuinely, like
the it works.
It's okay.
Think with me here for a second, right?
From first principles. The is this
workable? Is this a workable solution?
Like clearly the calling convention is
the same, right? Um the underlying idea
seems sound as long as the
implementation of the shim functions is
correct, but
I will say for now it for like the
purpose of doing this, it is.
Um there isn't like some trick about
that here. Is this correct? Does this
work? Do you think this works?
>> [sighs]
>> No, I'm on stage asking you a question.
Of course it doesn't.
Um
it's a pain to trace this, because well,
for the first reason, it's just it
doesn't play nice with how I've been
tracking events this whole time.
Because you can't, like, pull in a Miri
context when you're in one of those
little seg fault shims because you're
not actually you don't have a stack and
everything set up. You just have like a
little bit of memory to work with. That
basically should just be a couple lines
of handwritten assembly. Um
So, this is what we've been sending the
whole time. We have been sending at the
end of the FFI call a vector of
everything that's happened. Here is all
the memory accesses. You're welcome.
But, when you're also allocating, you
need that allocation to happen like now
as you're running it cuz, you know, it
might actually do something with that
allocated memory, not just return
malloc.
Um
So, what you need to do then is like
actually allocate that with Miri. Like,
we pull in a pointer to the Miri like
interpreter context into that shim. We
smuggle it through a global because, of
course, we smuggle it through a global.
Um and we then, like, have to
instantiate Miri's context and then do
that memory allocation or deallocation.
And that might invalidate some of those
events because some of them might have
happened like on memory that's now
deallocated. So, then if you report it
all at the end, it's like, "Oh, you
accessed uninitialized memory." Or uh or
not uninitialized, sorry, unallocated
memory.
And then Miri complains.
Um so, we have to sync the events while
we're doing the deallocation.
So, we use those damn IPC channels
again. We just slap on in a mutex in a
global because that's the only damn way
you can sneak every anything into
uh those functions.
And you just apply them before doing the
allocation and deallocation. Okay, sure.
That was a bit of a tricky one because I
didn't actually tell you how uh the
allocation uh the the access handling is
done.
But, like
surely that is it, right? Like
obviously, this is now working. We have
handled our own internal logic about
this.
Uh we have
uh handled the case where
uh like the allocations mess of which
accesses are valid at any given time.
So, this works.
No.
Um it sucks so much.
It's such a pain because look, there's
cases we didn't consider. Libc can call
itself.
Libc is allowed to call itself. And
because libc is compiled against libc,
sometimes that call is inlined, but
sometimes it's not.
Which is the painful case here because
we've just been overriding the like
address at the instruction memory at the
instruction address. We do our
breakpoint and jumping into our own
shims. What if libc is trying to
internally use something about like the
free mechanism or whatever? Um and that
will only get trapped sometimes, so then
you're sometimes allocating with one
uh thing like with miri and sometimes
allocating with libc and sometimes
freeing with one and sometimes freeing
with the other and
Uh
this hurts.
Uh okay. So, let's figure that out. When
is this happening?
Uh Linux has this lovely thing, proc
self maps. You can see what is mapped at
the addresses in memory.
Um
and we can figure out where libc is
mapped.
We just parse that, right? It's it's
just a file. We can open it, we can
iterate through the lines, and
uh find the bit that has like like the
address range that will have uh the
address of in this case libc.so.6 just
as a random thing that won't get put
elsewhere.
Um yeah, uh this was
a lot of stupid iterator nonsense to
figure out exactly how to handle all the
possible permutations and combinations
of when we are in libc, when we're not,
when also a case I didn't mention
explicitly, when memory had been
allocated uh with uh like malloc proper
at some point, um and then we like let's
say it's from lib C, and then it gets
passed back to us, and then we have to
free it with lib C. So, we need to
figure out if the memory belongs to lib
C or whether it belongs to Miri. Do you
understand why I went insane? This I
need you to picture where I was when I
wrote this code. I was at my desk
on the second floor of a little house
down in the suburbs here.
Um I was very sleep deprived. I was It
was probably 3:00 or 4:00 a.m. when I
wrote these particular lines.
Um I had just woken up a couple hours
ago to be clear.
Uh because this had become my sleep
schedule trying to work on this
nonsense.
Um and I was
desperate to just get something working.
This is not nice code. You don't want
this merged in your compiler. Who's
going to maintain this?
Well, thankfully this is not merged yet.
I need to fix it. It's my
responsibility. Uh lucky for you.
But, it did actually work this time
after doing all this nonsense. It passed
checks on CI.
This needs to be merged still. This
needs some clean-up, but it works. It's
there on a branch. You can just use it
if you clone that branch.
Okay. So, where are we? The first part
of this, the tracing of accesses to
memory, that's merged. That's been
merged for a while. You should go use
it. People have been using it. Uh you
pass this flag alongside the list of SOs
to link against. Yes, that could be done
a lot more nicely.
Uh it will be done a lot more nicely.
There's a big to-do list. Don't worry
about it. There's a very big to-do list,
and please contribute to it by telling
me your idea for how I could make this
better.
Um diesel folks have apparently been
testing some of their stuff with native
lib tracing. They can't get all of the
tests run currently because it requires
callback support, which
I'm not going to say my opinions on that
right now. Um
But that is the thing that I'm going to
be working on. That you can do this.
Like the whole point of this talk is
here's a crazy thing. Here's how I
willed it into existence despite reality
telling me it's a load of crap. Right?
You can have multiple threads running
natively. You can just park a thread and
then restart it in Miri scheduler. Like
Miri lets you model uh concurrency. So,
why couldn't you just do that? Why
couldn't you do callbacks? libffi, which
we already use for some of the actual
setup of FFI nonsense does uh have some
support for creating a custom callback.
You can just do that.
You could There is a world in the future
where uh
you could just like pass an arbitrary
function pointer into FFI and have it be
called across 18 threads simultaneously
in Miri and it still detects at least a
bunch of UB.
So, what about me?
Well, now I work on Rust. That's good. I
work on Rust partially because of this
because
this apparently made me uh the subject
of a lot of gossip on the internal uh
forums. Um
I have heard many things from many
people about Oh god, Ralph told me about
this stupid crap you made. Um
>> [laughter]
>> I know.
I appreciate you. Um and also Miri is
now unsound. So,
you're welcome. I may I I I heard you
like unsoundness, so we put some
unsoundness in the unsoundness detector.
And I have this amazing
This is a sticker on the official Rust
community Discord server.
This is PR review that I got from Ralph.
But I wouldn't have made it here without
a bunch of people, especially the latter
three things on the list, but very
importantly, the first three as well.
Um uh first four. Uh Ralph and Ollie did
a lot of work reviewing all of this. It
was genuinely a huge pain to review, and
it took so many iterations, and I didn't
really know what I was doing. This was
my first major contribution to Rust, and
honestly, only my second or third like
actual big Rust project. The code was
awful at the start especially. Like God,
what was I doing when I was setting up
like the custom allocation for
uh the memory that we were going to map
here. God, that's awful code to look at.
Uh xc, of course, for just taking the
time to like build a nice feature set uh
into uh disassembler so that I can
eventually expand all of this, and also
so that it's less flaky. There are so
many things that Capstone bit me about
that I didn't mention here because,
you know, I want to be done like this
week with the talk. Um
also Astro Fox, the person who had set
up the previous implementation of RFI
and Miri, which is still there, right?
You can All of this is Linux-only for
now. For now, unless, you know, we got
any like Microsoft or Apple people who
want to help me do this on their
platforms with a kernel module. Hm? Hm?
No? Okay. Um
of course, the Capstone people, all of
my dependencies. Uh Capstone especially
was like very big. I used to use a
different disassembler at first, Iced,
which was x86-only.
Uh that was also very nice. So, thank
you to them as well. Of course, thank
you for whatever Neolithic farmer in
Ethiopia, however many thousands of
years ago, ran into coffee beans.
I am so grateful for that. I am thankful
for Monster Energy and my wife.
Uh also discredits.
If you're a good programmer, you need to
hold a grudge. You need to hold a big
grudge. These are the people and the
things that I hate.
I will have a no nice things to say
about any anything responsible on the
bottom part of this slide.
Sweaty, thanks.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> Thank you, Nia.
I have questions,
but more importantly, I hope people in
the audience do as well. I cannot see
anyone right now, but I think it's about
to be fixed.
Okay, I'm going to start on this aisle.
We're probably not going to get to
everyone, but we'll do our best. All
right, let's start right here at the
front. Frank.
>> Uh
FFI so a lot of FFI things
sounded very like low-level interacting
with C and stuff. What happens if you
interact with some other managed
language like I don't know with Java or
how about their memory? Does that
just translate into where their runtime
does use malloc in the end somehow or
does it not work at all?
>> Great question.
Um the
currently this implementation treats
everything as like at the most low level
possible, right? This is effectively
would be a fallback if we had some
multiple levels above for better
interrupt with say Java for instance.
But eventually everything will either
use lib C or will directly just use like
mmap or sbrk
to allocate memory. They need to get the
memory somehow.
This is discussed the actually
interesting part of handling lib C. The
I also have on the same branch a way to
handle
specifically mmap and sbrk mmap in
particular
which is much simpler because ptrace
actually lets you nicely shim like
syscalls and you can just log down,
okay, this is the
address, right? Of the of the memory
that
um
was allocated via mmap and this is the
size and that's super easy. That's like
worked first try. It took me 20 minutes
to write.
So, yes, everything will be caught by
this. There is no special case handling
for Java or whatever.
>> Um what kind of stuff do you check at
the boundaries? Like do you check um
like value validity? Do you check like
tree borrows stuff? I know that's
[snorts] not fully decided, but you
know.
>> So, tree borrows or stack borrows in
general are not
really directly translatable into this
because this requires exposed provenance
semantics
uh on the pointer side. So, you need to
assume that pointers may might alias,
which is also just necessary when you're
working with assembly in general because
you just have a direct list of, you
know, what happened. You can't really
reason about
uh how you got there or like the
programming language that was initially
compiled cuz you can't figure that out
from just looking at the assembly. So,
uh but on the other hand, like for stuff
like uh value validity or whatever,
that's all just written back to Miri
state. So, whenever Miri would have a
check about something being valid or
invalid, after the FFI call, it would
trigger UB or not if it was uh actually
okay.
>> Um so, what are the advantages of uh
doing all this 6F stuff as opposed to
just emulating the whole CPU?
>> I was hoping you'd get that one.
Um
that is one that I've been asked before.
Like you could maybe emulate a CPU, use
QEMU, right? Use whatever. Just write
down an interpreter for x86 assembly at
that point.
Um
the main advantage of this is that
there is a world where this actually
goes fast
uh because like if the code that we're
talking about here doesn't really
interact much with Miri's memory, like
say you're uh Vulcan or something, and
you are like a Vulcan library, and
you're just mostly interacting with your
own memory, passing a couple things back
and forth.
Like it's not impossible to use this uh
in principle to like render a thing to
the screen at some point.
Um and so, and also there there is the
issue that like using QEMU or such would
mean you don't have access to like
arbitrary system libraries. This means
you could just link against a random SO.
You don't even have to know like what it
is. It will just have all of your
system's run time because it's just
actually running like it is a thing
being called. Which would be a pain to
emulate in QEMU or such.
>> Um, so I was wondering since this seems
to work with arbitrary FFI. Suppose I
have like a free standing C program that
I just wrote from
Could I run that under Miri now and
check if it does any undefined memory
accesses?
>> Yes, big asterisk.
Um, namely you first off this does this
not supported right now, but you could
just have like a one-line program of
Rust that just calls that
as the only thing it does and run that
with Miri. It would still be pretty
limited on what it does. This
effectively would just emulate like uh,
like ASan on LLVM if you're familiar
with that. It would sanitize that you're
not
uh, like double freeing or um, accessing
freed memory.
But it would not do more than that on
like in the FFI code.
>> Hi, thanks for the talk. Um, I was
wondering on which set of crates you are
testing this at the moment and what the
run time overhead is.
>> So, the I I currently this is being
tested with Miri CI because again
there's a lot more to do. I just have a
few handwritten tests that emulate the
ugly corner cases that I ran into of
uh, what needs to be traced, right? Like
um, having for instance, you know
allocating with lib C malloc which Miri
does directly shim on the rust side and
then passing that and then freeing that
with a normal native free call on the C
side.
I'm not testing this against any crates
yet because I want to do more. The
implementation is not done at this
point. As I like there was a whole thing
here of I I have more things that I want
to do. I have more plans. Then
afterwards again there are the diesel
folks who have started to try to test
some of this stuff. And upon that
working I'd be very interested to see
how many more things I can expand this
to. It's mostly just I don't know who
uses Miri's FFI already. I don't think
it's that many people.
And on the runtime overhead well it says
8000 seg fault a second a seg fault to
memory access.
It's not very fast.
You can make that faster but again
current implementation is mostly just
meant to be like does this work for at
least a simple toy program and it does
but there are definitely things to do to
optimize this further.
There is again a world where you could
just like have a little kernel module
instead because ptrace is really slow
and also having a faster disassembler
would help. A good chunk of the time is
spent like disassembling instructions.
>> Okay we've got one more question in the
center here and then we're going to have
to go to the break.
>> What prevents this from working on Mac
OS right now?
>> Ptrace is bad on Mac OS but Mac has Mac
OS has its own debugging interface and
if you were to just also we need an
equivalent for proc self maps but I
believe that's also very much doable.
So what's missing is just someone needs
to plug this in to the other API but
otherwise would work.
>> Lovely and on that slightly cursed
ptrace note thank you once again to Nia.
>> [applause]
>> Woo!